Register of the Lincoln Hutchinson papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Lincoln Hutchinson papers
1915-1939
68047
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, and reports, relating to American Relief Administration activities, food conditions in Germany following World War I, and technical assistance provided by American engineers in the Soviet Union.
Hutchinson, Lincoln.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1968.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Lincoln Hutchinson (1866–1940) was born in San Francisco, California. He graduated from the University of California-Berkeley in 1889 and received in M.A. in economics from Harvard University. He held many positions during his career: professor of economics and commerce at Berkeley; dean of the College of Letters and Science at Berkeley; professor of economics and sociology at Stanford University; consular attaché in South America and Europe; director of relief in the American Relief Administration in Russia, Germany and Czechoslovakia after World War I; and technical advisor in Czechoslovakia under Jan Masaryk.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Lincoln Hutchinson papers consist of correspondence, speeches and writings, travel documents, and American Relief Administration office records. His writings include “American Engineers in Russia,” two different essays in which Hutchinson describes technical assistance provided by American engineers to the Soviet Union. The travel documents series includes his passport from 1920–1922, when he was in Europe working for the A.R.A.. Finally, the American Relief Administration office records series contains a comprehensive report on food conditions in post-World War I Germany (1923). It also contains the constitution of the A.R.A., proposed amendments to the constitution of the A.R.A., Hutchinson’s lobbying to merge the A.R.A. with other relief programs, as well as his personal reminiscences of Herbert Hoover, "The Chief," as an individual and as an administrator.
American Relief Administration.; Engineering--Soviet Union.; Engineers.; World War, 1914-1918--Civilian relief.; World War, 1914-1918--Germany.
- Alphabetical correspondence, 1915-1939
  - Adams, Ephraim Douglass, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Babcock, Kendric C., 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Batchelder, Samuel F., 1923-1925 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bonnevalle, Richard W., 1929 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bowman, Isaiah, 1918-1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Carroll, Philip H., 1923-1931 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Causey, W.B., 1922-1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clements, Melbourne, 1925-1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cornell, Irwin H., 1931 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cottrell, F.C., 1929 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cross, Wilbur L., 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Croy, Ulric J., 1923-1929 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dohrmann, Fred, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Duval, W.S., 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Durych, Eugen, 1923-1926 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Donald, William G., 1931 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Edgeworth, F.Y., 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Golder, Frank Alfred, 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Gregg, John H., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Cheron, Dr. Andre, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Grosbach, I.H., 1931 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Gunn, Roy E., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Gunn, Selskar M., 1921 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Hale, David C., 1917 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Henderson, Victor H., 1924-1925 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Herter, Christian A., 1922 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hess, R.H., 1923 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Hunt, Thomas F., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Kelly, Harold R., 1928 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Kerner, Robert J., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Kovaleff, John W., 1931 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Krueger, J.W., 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Lehmer, Derrick N., 1924-1927 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Ling, Ernest E., 1923 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Lipman, Fred L., 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Litzow, A., 1921-1926 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Loben Sels, P.J. von, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Logan, James A., 1919-1925 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Maagher, Tom, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - MacKenzie, May, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Manship, George, 1916-1927 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Mitchell, Douglas C., 1926 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Moir, Ernest W., 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Momiyama, H., 1915 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Moses, Bernard, 1924-1928 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Murphy, M.F., 1922-1928 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Noyes, George R., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Patterson, A.M., 1922-1929 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Pierce, Edward Allen, 1923-1929 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Pike, H.H., 1926-1928 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Pugna, Gwen B., 1924-1928 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Reed, W.G., 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Ringland, Arthur C., 1931 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Rosentreter, Grover, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Rugg, Walter A., 1926-1928 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Sproule, William, 1924-1930 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Stevenson, T.P., 1928 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Strachey, J., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Strong, Austin, 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Wahren, I., 1930 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Wells, M.R., 1930 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Woltman, A.E., 1926 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Miscellaneous, 1923-1939 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Chronological correspondence, 1912-1923 (Boxes 3-4)
  Series of notebooks featuring letters written by Lincoln Hutchinson to an unlabelled recipient from the period 1912-1923. Arranged chronologically.
  - August 1912-July 1913, 1912-1913 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - December 1916-July 1916 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - June 1917-July 1918 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - July 1918-January 1919 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - February 1919-July 1919 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - July 1919-October 1919 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - January 1920-September 1921 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - October 1921-November 1923 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Writings
  - "American engineers in Russia,", after 1929 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "American engineers in Russia,", after 1936 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Passport, 1920 -1922 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- American Relief Administration (A.R.A.) office records, 1914-1935
  - Report on food conditions in Germany, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - A.R.A. Association I, 1914-1933 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes announcements, correspondence, agendas, invitations, memorials to the late Frank A. Golder, and other documents pertaining to Russia, Germany, and Czechoslovakia.
  - A.R.A. Association II, 1929 - 1935 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes correspondence with the A.R.A.'s Children's Fund, Inc. and amendments to the A.R.A. constitution